LALIT VARMA

Senior Data and Insights Analyst

Sydney, NSW | +61 480 162 911 | VARMA.31@GMAIL.COM

in linkedin.com/in/varmalalit

Summary

Self-motivated Data Analyst offering 11 years of leadership experience across various industries. Methodical with significant experience in data mining and analysis using advanced tools. Excellent problem-solver with a history of automating processes and driving operational enhancements. Passionate and committed to learning new skills.

Sas. Certified Advanced Programmer for SAS'9



Work experience

Technical Lead Cognizant 2014-05 - Present

SENIOR DATA ANALYST

2020-06 - present

Telstra, Sydney, AU

- Utilized Power BI to create several reports and dashboards for Mass Market fulfilment and Transport Analysis
- Developed complex calculated measures using Data Analysis Expression (DAX)
- Created W/H operations report which identified ageing tickets to prioritize work and reduce complaints.
- Tracked performance of stores, regions, channels, Lines of Business, using orders, backorders, returns and transport data
- Created HITT report to track service tickets created, which helped identify trend, cause and severity of tickets for each assigned team
- Identified high order value back-ordered items using Pareto charts to maximize profits with minimal efforts
- Presented and implemented a business case to reduce transport costs by 10% (\$4M)
- Participated in requirements meetings and data mapping sessions to understand business needs; Designed and developed schema data models. Identified and documented detailed business rules and use cases based on requirements analysis
- Built library of models and reusable knowledge-base assets to produce consistent and streamlined business intelligence results
- Worked closely with Business Operations Principal to maintain optimum levels of communication to effectively and efficiently complete projects

SAS DATA ANALYST

2019-09 - 2020-05

Suncorp Bank, Sydney, AU

- Researched, designed and implemented scalable applications for data extraction, analysis, retrieval and tagging for Payment Card Industry Data Security Standard (PCI DSS)
- Used Regex and Luhn algorithm to identify and redact PANs after verification
- Built databases and table structures to log scanning and redaction process orchestrated by control tables
- Documented process flow and potential workarounds for tweaking runs on the confluence
- Enhanced and automated process to load data and table definitions to ThoughtSpot database using SAS and UNIX; reduced processing time by 98%
- Trained and mentored junior developers and engineers, teaching skills in SAS and improving overall team performance.

- Participated in requirements meetings and data mapping sessions to understand business needs
- Developed, tested, implemented codes in production code changes required for IFRS9 using Bitbucket
- Provided technical support for production runs
- Delivered data and technology solutions to both internal and external customers
- Developed Unix and SAS macro snippets to automate tasks such as archiving monthly production logs, test data, compared production jobs completed against the previous month for timeline comparisons to improve efficiency.
- Lead offshore team, provided business and technical knowledge, delegated daily tasks and supervised their activities.
- Automated process to update control tables which reduced effort from 2 hours to 5 minutes
- Created a solution to perform auditing task, which read data from source and target file and compares md5 sum values, provided other check results explaining mismatch. Automated process to reduce time and effort by 90 %.

SAS DATA ENGINEER

2016-12 - 2018-09

ING Bank N.V, Amsterdam, NL

Netherlands

- Used advanced SAS procedures and functions to develop code for Customer Profitability.
- Created effective rerun plans after release without impacting the current production run.
- Optimized and automated legacy manual processes and codes, automated disk space management, reduced manual effort from 3 days to 10 min.
- Prepared documentation, technical design and test implementation plan for Audit
- Performed testing to find bugs and troubleshoot SAS issues before application launch, analyzed SAS logs to determine production errors' root cause
- Worked on several ad-hoc tasks to provide answers to business users

SAS DEVELOPER

2015-08 - 2016-09

CITIBANK, Bangalore, IN

- Read data from disparate sources, such as flat files, data warehouse, and native SAS datasets, to perform analysis to measure campaigns' performance.
- Tracked performance of credit card marketing campaigns and provided data insights to modelling team to help them optimize their model
- Streamlined and automated process by creating macro-driven codes Created QC process for analyzing campaign reads performance, increased efficiency by 80%.
- Tested and migrated existing jobs to GRID server
- Worked effectively with cross-functional design teams to create data solutions that elevated client experience and significantly improved overall functionality and performance.
- Revised, modularized and updated old code bases to modern development standards, reducing operating costs and improving functionality

SAS DATA ANALYST

2014-05 - 2015-07

Barclays US, Pune, IN

- Analyzed existing codes to optimize and migrate from SAS environment to Microsoft SQL Server. Created Business requirement documents from existing codes by performing reverse engineering. Provided technical and business inputs to the development team
- Removed redundant programs to make the process streamlined and efficient. Performed data reconciliation at granular and report level across both platforms
- Prepared a variety of different written communications, reports and documents to ensure smooth development
- Reduced processing time by 50%.

SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER

2011-03 - 2014-04

- Analyzed data as per business requirements, which helped clients make critical business decisions, implemented business rules to create data and reports. Created graphs, tabular reports, KPIs charts using SAS/MACROS.
- Worked closely with other business analysts, on-shore partners to deliver solutions for mission-critical applications
- Developed Portal hits application, which tracked usage of all existing and newly developed reports
- Created High Claimant report, which provided insights on the high value of claims across states and channels with associated sales agents over the period to identify patterns which helped in identifying a potential threat to business
- Created proof of concept for migrating existing reporting to Tableau, which increased revenue, and reduced manual efforts by 30%

Education

Bachelor of Engineering: Electrical

2005-08 - 2010-05

Pune University | 7.2 GPA | Ranked 9th in the University

Skills

- Advanced SAS
- Power BI
- Bitbucket
- Unix
- R
- Technical acumen
- Leadership
- Flexible & Adaptable
- Critical thinking
- Self-motivated professional

Certifications

- Data Analyst Associate Microsoft
- Certified Advanced Programmer for SAS, SAS
- Linear Regression, Coursera
- Machine Learning, Coursera